Guide to the M. Perry Chapman papers, 1963-2010.
Chapman, M. Perry papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
M. Perry Chapman papers, 1963-2010.
8453
Chapman, M. Perry.
27 cubic feet, 2 map case folders
Professional records, reports, architectural plans, and publications.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection consists of M. Perry Chapman's professional records. Includes project files, reports, master plans, and publications related to campus planning.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
M. Perry Chapman was born in Cooperstown, New York and graduated from Cornell University with a bachelor of architecture degree in 1960. After working for the city planning bureau in Rochester, New York, he joined Sasaki Associates in Watertown, Massachusetts in 1964, where he worked for the reminder of his career. His early projects were master plans and environmental impact studies for large projects such as the 1980 Winter Olympics in Lake Placid, New York and the 1984 Summer Olympics in Los Angeles. He then headed the firm's campus planning practice and worked with dozens of universities across the United States, focusing in this area for most of his career. He was also a member of the Belmont, Massachusetts Planning Board and the Metropolitan Area Planning Council. He wrote and spoke frequently on the theory and practice of planning, publishing his book "American Places: In Search of the Twenty-First Century Campus" in 2006. That year, the American Planning Association's New England Chapter awarded him their Distinguished Achievement Award, and he received the K.C. Parsons Founder's Award for Distinguished Achievement in Higher Education Planning from the Society for College and University Planning in 2008. The Society for College and University Planning and the Hideo Sasaki Foundation award the annual Perry Chapman Prize in his honor.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Collection consists of M. Perry Chapman's professional records. Includes project files, reports, master plans, and publications related to campus planning.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Chapman, M. Perry.
Subjects:
City planning -- United States.; Campus planning -- United States.; Universities and colleges -- United States -- Planning.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Colleges and Universities
Boxes 1-24, Mapcase Folder 1
Alabama - Georgia
Illinois - New York
North Carolina - Wyoming; Canada and Other Non-U.S. Campuses
Business School Related
Series II. Olympic Games
Boxes 3, 8, 14
Series III. City Planning
Boxes 2-3, 6-11, 13-14, 17, 20, 24, Mapcase Folder 1
Series IV. General Planning and Administrative Files
Boxes 12, 19-21, 25-27
Series V. Media and Memorabilia
Boxes 6, 28 and Mapcase Folder 2
Plans - Digital Files
Presentations and Papers - Digital Files
Memorabilia
CONTAINER LIST
- College and University Plans
  - Alabama - Georgia
    - Alabama
      - Auburn University, 2001 (Box 1)
        Draft Planning Issues Paper Comprehensive Master Plan
      - Auburn University, 2001 (Box 1)
        A Precinct Plan for the College of Sciences and Mathematics
      - Auburn University, 2001 (Box 1)
        Land Use Plan
      - Auburn University, 2002 (Box 1)
        Campus Master Plan Draft Final Executive Summary
      - Auburn University, 2002 (Box 15)
        Comprehensive Master Plan draft final
      - Auburn University, 2003 (Box 1)
        Site Development Concept
      - Auburn University Research Park, 2003 (Box 1)
        Interim Site Analysis Report
      - Auburn University Research Park, 2003 (Box 1)
        Site Accommodation Study
      - Auburn University, 2006 (Box 1)
        Campus Master Plan Draft
      - Auburn University, 2001-2002 (Box 23, Folder 6-9)
        Project Files
      - Auburn University, 2005-2007 (Box 23, Folder 10-11)
      - Auburn University, 1999-2002 (Box 23, Folder 12-23)
        Project Files.
        Contains copies of materials with dates from 1988-1997
      - Auburn University, 1999-2002 (Box 24, Folder 1-2)
    - Arizona
      - University of Arizona, Undated (Map-case Folder 1)
        Master Plan renewal design bid sketches and plans
    - Arkansas
      - University of Arkansas, 1998 (Box 1)
        Campus Master Plan
      - University of Arkansas at Little Rock, 1987 (Box 1)
        Landscape Master Plan
      - University of Arkansas at Little Rock, 1986 (Box 1)
        Appendices
      - University of Arkansas at Little Rock, 1985 (Box 1)
        Comprehensive Master Plan
    - California
      - California State University, 1997 (Box 2)
        Master Plan
      - California State University, Undated (Box 2)
        CSUMB Master Plan Appendix
      - California State University - Monterey Bay, 1996 (Box 11)
        Master Plan Work Book
      - Harvey Mudd College, 2001 (Box 1)
        Analysis of Current and Regionally Appropriate Landscapes
      - Harvey Mudd College, 1989 (Box 1)
        Master Plan Summary Report
      - Harvey Mudd College, 1989 (Box 1)
        Draft Master Plan Summary Report
      - Los Angeles Southwest College, 2003 (Box 1)
        Facilities Master Plan
      - Menlo School and Menlo College, 1994 (Box 2)
        Site Capacity Analysis
      - Mills College, 2008 (Box 11)
        Celebrating the Landscape Heritage of Mills College
      - Pitzer College, Undated (Box 2)
      - Santa Clara University, Undated (Box 2)
        Five Year Capital Plan and Campus Development Guidelines
      - University of California, Berkeley, 1999 (Box 2)
        New Century Plan: Preliminary Campus Strategies Workshop Synthesis Core Values
      - University of California, Berkeley, 1999 (Box 2)
        New Century Plan: Regional and Campus Analysis Themes and Propositions Regional Plan Options
      - University of California, Berkeley, 2004 (Box 2)
        Landscape Heritage Plan
      - University of California, Berkeley, 1990-2005 (Box 2)
        Long Range Development Plan
      - University of California, Berkeley, 1998 (Box 24, Folder 18)
      - University of California, Irvine, 1997 (Box 12)
        East Campus Master Planning Study
    - Colorado
      - Colorado Academy, 1985 (Box 1)
        Master Plan Site Reconnaissance and Analysis
      - Colorado Academy, 1985 (Box 1)
        Master Plan Program Information and Impact Analysis
      - Colorado Academy, 1985 (Box 11)
      - University of Colorado at Colorado Springs, 2000 (Box 1)
        The Lange Development Plan and Master Plan
      - University of Colorado, Boulder Campus, Undated (Box 2)
        Reference Notebook on Campus Development
    - Connecticut
      - Central Connecticut State College, 1971 (Box 8)
      - Wesleyan, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Delaware
      - University of Delaware, 1968 (Box 4)
        Long Range Development Guide
    - Florida
      - Florida State, 1992 (Box 4)
        Interview Supplement Campus Master Plan Updates
      - University of Florida, 1997 (Box 22, Folder 20)
      - University of South Florida, 2000 (Box 7)
        Evaluation and Appraisal Report Data Sheets
      - University of South Florida, Undated (Box 10)
        Project Notebook for Master Plan Update for the Campuses at: Tampa/Lakeland, St. Petersburg, Sarasota
      - University of South Florida, 2000 (Box 16)
        Strategic Plan
      - University of South Florida, 2002 (Box 16)
        Sarasota/Manatee Campus - Preliminary Evaluation and Appraisal Report
      - University of South Florida, 1992-1994 (Box 22, Folder 24-27)
        Various campuses
      - University of South Florida, 1991-1994 (Box 23, Folder 1-4)
      - University of South Florida, 1996 (Box 22, Folder 21)
        Teaching Enhancement Center materials
      - University of South Florida, 1992-1995 (Box 25, Folder 8-16)
      - University of South Florida, Undated (Box 25, Folder 23)
        Plans
      - University of South Florida, St. Petersburg, 1995 (Box 10)
      - University of South Florida - St. Petersburg Central Area, 1999 (Box 19, Folder 24)
        #91491.01
      - University of South Florida, St. Petersburg, 1996 (Box 22, Folder 19)
        Pediatric Research Building
      - University of South Florida, St. Petersburg, 1996-1997 (Box 22, Folder 22)
      - University of South Florida, Sarasota, 1995 (Box 7)
      - University of South Florida, Sarasota, 1995 (Box 12)
      - University of South Florida, Tampa, 1995 (Box 7)
        Master Plan Update
      - University of South Florida, Tampa, 1992 (Box 10)
      - University of South Florida, Tampa, 2002 (Box 12)
        Campus draft Master Plan Update
      - University of South Florida, Tampa, 2002 (Box 12)
        Campus Master Plan Update
      - University of South Florida, Tampa, 1994 (Box 16)
      - University of South Florida, Tampa, 2000 (Box 16)
        Evaluation and Appraisal Report
      - University of South Florida, Tampa, 1999 (Box 19, Folder 22-23)
        Amendment #81640
      - University of South Florida, Tampa, 1999 (Box 19, Folder 25)
        Entrance Study #91491
      - University of South Florida, Tampa, 1993, 1996-1998 (Box 22, Folder 11-18)
      - University of South Florida, Tampa, 1994 (Box 23, Folder 5)
        Drawings and plans
      - University of South Florida - St. Petersburg and Tampa, 1993 (Box 22, Folder 23)
    - Georgia
      - Georgia Tech, 1991 (Box 1)
        Site Feasibility Study Tech Lawn Central
      - Georgia Tech, 1991 (Box 1)
        Site Feasibility Study Phase I Housing/Natatorium
      - University of Georgia, 1997 (Box 1)
        Physical Master Planning Template Reference Guide
  - Illinois - New York
    - Illinois
      - Heartland Community College, Undated (Box 8)
      - Northern Illinois University, 1988 (Box 5)
        Master Plan Report
      - Northern Illinois University, 1987 (Box 8)
        Concept Plan Report
      - Northern Illinois University, 1987 (Box 8)
        An evaluation of space inventory
      - Northern Illinois University, 1990 (Box 8)
        Report of Findings/ Recommendations
      - Northwestern University, 2007 (Box 8)
        Framework Plan
      - Northwestern University, 2004-2006 (Box 24, Folder 19-23)
      - Northwestern University, 2001-2004 (Box 25, Folder 1-3)
        Also contains copy of material from 1991
      - Northwestern University, 2004 (Box 25, Folder 4-7)
        Project Files for Southeast Campus
      - University of Chicago, 1979 (Box 1)
        Summary Campus Development Plan, Proposed Guidelines for the Future
      - University of Chicago, 1979 (Box 1)
        Medical Center Parking Facilities Assessment May
      - University of Chicago, 1979 (Box 1)
        Campus Development Plan
      - University of Chicago, 1979 (Box 5)
      - University of Chicago, Undated (Box 15)
      - University of Illinois at Chicago, Undated (Box 2)
        Master Plan Summery
      - University of Illinois at Urbana-Champagne, 1986 (Box 8)
        North Campus Master Plan
      - University of Illinois at Urbana-Champagne, 1986 (Box 8)
        South Campus Master Plan Executive Summary
      - University of Illinois at Urbana-Champagne, 1990 (Box 8)
        South Farms Master Plan Executive Summary
      - University of Illinois at Urbana-Champagne, Undated (Box 8)
        South Farms Master Plan
      - University of Illinois at Urbana-Champagne, 1986 (Box 8)
        South Campus Master Plan
      - University of Illinois at Urbana-Champagne, Undated (Box 8)
        North Campus Master Plan Executive Summary
      - University of Illinois at Urbana-Champagne, 1989 (Box 8)
        Central Campus Master Plan draft issues and analysis report
      - University of Illinois at Urbana-Champagne, 1989 (Box 8)
        Central Campus Master Plan
      - University of Illinois at Urbana-Champagne, Undated (Box 8)
        Historic Preservation
      - University of Illinois at Urbana-Champagne, Undated (Box 8)
        Historic Preservation Appendices
      - University of Illinois at Urbana-Champagne, 1986 (Box 8)
        North Campus Master Plan draft site analysis and inventory
      - University of Illinois at Urbana-Champagne, 1991 (Box 8)
        Willard Airport Area Land Use Goals and Strategies Report
      - Wheaton College, 1987 (Box 4)
        Master Plan Composite Inventory Report
      - Wheaton College, 1988 (Box 8)
        Athletic Facility Program Summary
    - Indiana
      - Indiana State University, 1986-1995 (Box 8)
      - Indiana State University, 1986-1995 (Box 13)
      - Indiana University, 1997 (Box 4)
        Interview Supplement Master Planning Consultant Services
    - Iowa
      - Iowa State University, 1992 (Box 8)
    - Kentucky
      - University of Louisville, 1993 (Box 2)
    - Louisiana
      - Tulane University, 1978 (Box 8)
        Master Plan Study
    - Maine
      - University of Maine, 2008-2009 (Box 13)
        Master Plan Report Executive Summary
      - University of Maine, 2008-2010 (Box 13)
    - Maryland
      - Montgomery College, 1990 (Box 9)
      - Morgan State University, 1997 (Box 2)
      - St. Mary's College of Maryland, 1986-1995 (Box 1)
      - United States Naval Academy, 1990 (Box 4)
        Athletic Facilities Master Plan Existing Facilities Evaluation
    - Massachusetts
      - Boston College Lower Campus, 1985 (Box 4)
        Planning Status Report
      - Boston University, 1986-1996 (Box 12)
        Charles River Campus Master Plan
      - Curry College, 1989 (Box 4)
        Master Plan Inventory Report
      - Gordon College, 1990 (Box 4)
        Conceptual Land Use Plan
      - Hampshire College, 1966 (Box 8)
        Master Plan Studies
      - Harvard University, 2007 (Box 12)
        Plan for Harvard in Allston draft executive summary
      - Northeastern University, 1987 (Box 4)
        Boston Campus Master Plan
      - Northeastern University, 1999 (Box 4)
        Uncovering the Past: Northeastern University and its Environs
      - Northeastern University, 1986 (Box 4)
        Boston Campus Master Plan Concept Alternatives
      - Northeastern University, 1996 (Box 4)
        Diagnostic of Peer Institutions
      - Northeastern University, 1986 (Box 4)
        Campus Master Plan Executive Summary
      - Northeastern University, 1978 (Box 4)
        Campus Plan Study
      - Tufts University, Undated (Box 4)
        Campus Master Plans
      - Tufts University, 1986 (Box 4)
        Campus Master Plan Grafton Campus
      - Tufts University, 1986 (Box 13)
        Master Plan Grafton Campus
      - Tufts University, Undated (Box 13)
        Master Plan Medford/Somerville Campus
      - University of Massachusetts, Lowell, 1986 (Box 4)
      - University of Massachusetts, Lowell, 1985 (Box 4)
        Master Plan Facilities Analysis
      - University of Massachusetts, Lowell, 1985 (Box 4)
        Master Plan Academic Program Analysis and Master Plan Space Requirements
      - University of Massachusetts, Lowell, 1996 (Box 4)
        Gateway Campus Strategic Plan
      - University of Massachusetts, Lowell, 1996 (Box 4)
        Gateway Campus Strategic Plan Appendix
      - University of Massachusetts, Lowell, 1986 (Box 11)
        Master Plan Analysis of Existing Conditions and Projected Space Needs
      - University of Massachusetts, Lowell, 1985-1986, 1995-1997 (Box 22, Folder 4-10)
        # 51454.00 - Project Files
      - Wentworth Institute of Technology, 1991 (Box 4)
      - Worcester Polytechnical Institute, 1987 (Box 15)
      - Worcester Polytechnical Institute, 1988 (Box 15)
        Opportunities and constraints in the proposed business campus district
    - Michigan
      - The Lowry Education Center, 1995 (Box 1)
      - Michigan State University, 2001 (Box 8)
        2020 Vision: A community concept, Campus Master Plan Report
      - Michigan State University, 2000 (Box 20, Folder 14)
        Planning Principles and Parameters for Parking, Transportation, and Open Spaces
    - Missouri
      - University of Missouri, 2001 (Box 11)
        Botanic Garden Case Statement
      - University of Missouri, 1998 (Box 11)
        Hospitals and Clinics Health Sciences Master Plan
      - University of Missouri, 2002 (Box 11)
        Proposed New Building for the Human Environmental Sciences
      - University of Missouri, 2002 (Box 20, Folder 11)
        Various - mainly Southwest Campus Housing
      - University of Missouri, (2003) 2008 (Box 20, Folder 12)
        Working Papers
      - University of Missouri, 2004-2008 (Box 20, Folder 13)
      - University of Missouri, 2007-2008 (Box 20, Folder 16)
        Billing Summaries
      - University of Missouri, 2011 (Box 21, Folder 5)
        North Central Conference
      - University of Missouri - College of Agriculture, Food, and Natural Resources, 2007-2008 (Box 21, Folder 4)
        Handwritten notes
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 2006 (Box 2)
        MU Campus Master Plan Update Executive Summary
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 2006 (Box 2)
        MU Campus Master Plan Update Executive Summary - Draft
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 2009 (Box 2)
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 2010 (Box 2)
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, Undated (Box 2)
        Project Narrative: Technology Incubator Construction Project
      - University of Missouri- Columbia, 1988 (Box 6)
        Center for the Arts
        Concept by Pellham, Phillips and Hagerman
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 1998 (Box 11)
        Application as Campus Master Planning Advisor
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 2003 (Box 11)
        College Avenue Pedestrian Bridge
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 2001 (Box 11)
        The Art of Engineering
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 2001 (Box 11)
        Enrollment Management
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 2000 (Box 11)
        Residential Life Master Plan draft
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 2001 (Box 11)
        Residential Life Master Plan
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 2001 (Box 11)
        Virginia Avenue Housing and Dining Facility Schematic Design Report
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 2003 (Box 11)
        Performing Arts Center project file
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 2004-2007 (Box 20, Folder 7-10)
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 2003-2004 (Box 20, Folder 30)
        #81498.07 - Working papers
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 1999-2006 (Box 24, Folder 11)
        Master Plans
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 2003 (Box 24, Folder 12-14)
        Images for historic Study
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 2004 (Box 24)
        South Farm Master Plan
      - University of Missouri, Columbia, 2004 (Box 24, Folder 15-16)
        South Farm
      - University of Missouri, St. Louis, 1993 (Box 8)
      - University of Missouri, St. Louis, 1993 (Box 13)
      - University of Missouri, St. Louis, 2009 (Box 13)
    - New Hampshire
      - Keene State College, 1991 (Box 4)
        Master Plan Inventory and Issues Report
      - Keene State College, 1992 (Box 8)
      - University of New Hampshire, 1994 (Box 4)
        Playfields Master Plan
      - University of New Hampshire, Undated (Box 9)
        Campus Master Plan Draft Inventory and Issues Report
      - University of New Hampshire, 1990-1997 (Box 21, Folder 21-25)
      - University of New Hampshire, 1990 (Box 21)
        University Relations Strategic Plan
      - University of New Hampshire, 1991 (Box 21)
        Alumni Affairs and Development Strategic Plan
      - University of New Hampshire, 1991-1994 (Box 21, Folder 26-29)
      - University of New Hampshire, 1993-1994 (Box 22, Folder 1-3)
    - New Jersey
      - Princeton Forrestal Center, 1983 (Box 7)
        A Tenth Year Update draft
      - Princeton Forrestal Center, 1977 (Box 16)
        Planning Workbook
      - Princeton Forrestal Center, 1980 (Box 16)
        Storm water Management Phase II
      - Princeton Forrestal Center, 1981 (Box 16)
        Storm water Management Phase III
      - Princeton Forrestal Center, 1984 (Box 16)
      - Princeton Forrestal Center, Undated (Box 16)
        Environmental and Economic Feasibility Studies Summary Report
      - Princeton Forrestal Center, Undated (Box 16)
        brochure
      - Princeton Forrestal Center, Undated (Box 16)
        Design and Development Criteria
      - Princeton Forrestal Center, 1990 (Box 16)
        Traffic Impact Assessment
      - Princeton Forrestal Center, 1973 (Box 16)
        January 18th Presentation to Trustees
      - Princeton Forrestal Center, 1979 (Box 16)
        Interim Report on Development of Phase II
      - Princeton Forrestal Center, 1974 (Box 16)
        Concept for an entry sign system
      - Princeton Forrestal Center, 1983 (Box 16)
      - Princeton Forrestal Center, 1985 (Box 16)
        Traffic Study
      - Princeton Forrestal Center, 1984 (Box 16)
        Traffic Data Update
      - Princeton Forrestal Center, 1973, 1975 (Box 20, Folder 27)
        Planning Consultant's Supplement to Application Statement and Market Analysis
    - New Mexico
      - New Mexico Institute of Mining and Technology, 2000 (Box 12)
    - New York
      - Cornell University, Undated (Box 6)
        Master Plan - Maps
      - Cornell University, 1981 (Box 7)
        Evaluation of potential sites for the Performing Arts Center
      - Cornell University, 1988 (Box 7)
        Campus Plan draft
      - Cornell University Department of Architectural Services, 1998 (Box 7)
        Generic Office Building Site Accommodations Study: Wilson Lab
      - Cornell University: New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences, 1993 (Box 7)
        Master Plan Issues and Opportunities Report
      - Cornell University, Undated (Box 9)
        West Campus Circulation Study Appendix (3x)
      - Cornell University, 2003 (Box 9)
        Central Campus Transportation Study Preliminary Needs Assessment
      - Cornell University, 2002 (Box 9)
        North Campus Circulation Study
      - Cornell University, 2002 (Box 9)
        North Campus Circulation Study Appendix
      - Cornell University, 2003 (Box 9)
        Central Campus Transportation Study: Traffic Impacts of Preferred Scenario and Work Session PowerPoint
      - Cornell University, 2003 (Box 9)
        Central Campus Transportation Study: Executive Summary and Draft
      - Cornell University, 2003 (Box 9)
        Parking Structure Combined with the MVR North replacement building
      - Cornell University, Undated (Box 9)
        Misc. Project Papers
      - Cornell University, 1988 (Box 9)
      - Cornell University, 2004 (Box 9)
        Central Campus Transportation Study Executive Summary
      - Cornell University, 1999 (Box 9)
        North Campus Residential Initiative: Environmental Impact Statement
      - Cornell University, 1998, Undated (Box 9)
        Duffield Hall, Maps, and misc.
      - Cornell University, 2002 (Box 10)
        West Campus Circulation Study
      - Cornell University, Undated (Box 16)
        New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences proposal to provide master planning services
      - Cornell University, 1993 (Box 16)
        New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences Master Plan Draft
      - Cornell University, 1992 (Box 16)
        A Strategic Framework for Campus Precinct Development
      - Cornell University, Undated (Box 16)
        University of the State of New York: Capital Assets Preservation Program
      - Cornell University, 1993 (Box 16)
        Various circulation, transportation and parking studies
      - Cornell University, 1993 (Box 16)
        New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences Master Plan Round II
      - Cornell University, 2005-2010 (Box 25, Folder 17-18)
        Architectural Advisory Committee
      - Iona College, 1997 (Box 4)
      - State University of New York at Buffalo Amherst Campus, 1970 (Box 9)